Okay welcome or welcome back to
WordPress Accessibility Day everyone.
My name is Amanda. I'm based
here in Cleveland, Ohio.
It is not yet daylight out
so it seems a bit dark
and I will be your host for
the next three sessions here.
I have the honor of
introducing the next session
which is the Digital Transformation
or the Social Digital Transformation
with Merary Alvarado.
A little bit about Merary.
She is a software engineer
and accessibility evangelist with
six plus years of proven experience
in executing development and
leading accessibility processes
in digital strategies
for Fortune 100 clients.
She has collaborated to create
national standards and best practices
to be applicable across Costa Rica
for digital, educational
and physical environments
to improve their independent living.
She is the co-lead of the Accessibility
Web Costa Rica a public group on Facebook
which develops digital content, training,
conferences, events, webinars in Spanish
to create awareness about the importance
of accessibility in the digital era.
So welcome to Merary, very
excited to hear her talk.
Please feel free to add your questions
to the YouTube chat feed there
and we can answer those at the end.
So let's get started.
Perfect! So thank you very
much for that introduction.
I would like to start
sharing my screen right now.
Okay so, thank you so much
for that introduction.
I'm really happy to be here
participating right now in this event
because it's the first one!
I'm really happy to be participant
because it's important
at least for Costa Rica
because we are from
a Latin American country
being presenting today here
is really really great for us.
So accessibility as a
Digital Transformation
or Social Digital Transformation.
What do we—
what we can say about that?
So I would like to start telling a story.
When I was 16 years old I was sat
down at the first row at a bus
just waiting to go to the high school.
And suddenly, one woman stood up in
front of the door bus carrying a baby.
She was started talking with her
hands and I didn't understand.
I was shocked, neither the bus
driver he was shocked as well.
And suddenly the answer of the bus
driver was close the door in her face.
I just remembered the feeling.
To feel so bad going to the high school
and I couldn't forget her face
behind the door with the baby.
She wait for a couple of
seconds and then leave.
That experience for me was important
and in terms of disabilities,
it was my first experience
talking or interacting with a person
with disabilities.
Even though I was 16 years old,
I didn't have the opportunity to talk
before, with any person with disabilities,
at that moment with a deaf person.
One of the funny things is that
after like 10 years I met Martha.
Martha was that woman that
was at that time, at that moment
and she assigned me right now the sign that
we have in Costa Rica.
She gave me my name for
the deaf community.
So I would like to say thank you
very much for being here
to watching my presentation.
I'm super happy you are here
in YouTube just watching that.
So I would like to start saying one thing.
There is important to mention
a couple of important concepts
that we need to understand when
we are talking about accessibility.
Sometimes we assume that accessibility
is just technical aspects,
but I think it implies more other concepts.
For example, the first one that I
would like to start mentioning is
Inclusive Economy
and you probably said, I'm sorry Merary
we are talking about accessibility.
So what Inclusive Economy needs
to be related with that conversation?
Well a lot.
When we are talking about inclusive
economies, we are talking about
the balance to include all people,
doesn't matter the background,
doesn't matter the level
or savviness in technology
or the way the color looks
like, the gender—doesn't matter.
Neither the disability.
So that's why talking about
inclusive economy is important,
because we are entrepreneurs,
we have businesses,
we lead some projects
and thinking about this is really important
to create more accessible products
and services to many users as possible
and of course try to be more
inclusive with all of users.
Now one of the other important concepts
that we need to understand is Disability.
Because if we want to create
accessible content,
we need to understand
what disability means.
And actually an accessibility,
well sorry disability, is complex.
It's not easy to understand.
It has too many variables and
we definitely understand that.
But one of the things that I really
need to mention here or to recall
is that disability is not the problem.
We need to understand
what disability means,
but disability is not the problem,
it's usually the infrastructure, the
way that we create the sites,
the type of services.
If they are so complex.
So we need to create more
things that are accessible.
So that's why it's important to mention
that the complexity of those combinations
like the disability concept and
also what we have around of us,
it's important.
So I would like to make a question.
What do you understand about disabilities?
We already read about
the disability meaning,
but what do you
understand about disability?
Because if you don't understand the concept
in the way that we expect it,
we cannot create accessible websites.
And you probably said, what—
what are you talking about?
Well, usually when we think
about disabilities, we think in a—
we think about disabilities
with different perceptions.
We have some bias or we have assumptions.
We usually think about
disability in different levels.
For example, in Costa Rica
sometimes I heard that said,
oh poor babies, poor angels.
And we are limiting people with
disabilities to access some information,
because we are not properly
understanding what disability means.
And for example, we usually associate that
disabilities are always people who is deaf
or who is blind or who have
some physical disabilities,
but we have a range of many disability
types that we need to understand as well.
And other things that is
most related to business is
probably in our team or in our project,
we have a more accessible culture.
But what about our clients?
what about our business owners?
what about our team members?
what they think about disability?
So they are understanding
what is disability
and why it's important accessibility,
when they are creating
wireframes, for example,
or they are creating websites.
So that's important to mention.
So I would like to
just talk as a high level
about the different
disabilities that we have.
We have the permanent one
which is the one that we can see.
We can see people who is blind
or people who is deaf
or people with mobility impairments.
That's the permanent one.
Then we have the other which
is the one the temporary.
For example, you are fan
of rugby, martial arts,
or if you are fan of American football,
so sorry, if you have an injury,
you will be disabled for a couple of days.
You will not able to do the
things as the way you did before,
so you need to understand that some of
the things will be difficult for you,
but temporary.
Okay?
Then we have the third one
and it's the situational
and I would like to illustrate
that within the story.
As you can notice, I have an a
strong accent, Costa Rica accent.
The "r" is super strong
in Costa Rica accent.
And I will like, I love to visit,
I would like to to visit Korea.
And can you imagine me talking
in English with a Korean
citizen with also they
have a strong accent.
Well yes, that would be a
situational disability,
but I would like to clarify that
is not physical, is not mental,
it's just situational.
It's because the language.
And finally we have the
invisible disabilities
and nobody in this call is safe of that
because everyone has been suffer
these kind of disabilities,
at any time in your life.
So that's why it's
important to understand that
invisible disabilities
are really important now.
And why is this important?
When we know what is disability,
what are the types of disabilities,
we can definitely understand what
are the Internet Disabilities.
This classification
implies five main levels
like Visual, Hearing, Mobility &
Dexterity, Speech and Cognitive.
Being Cognitive the most
common in internet.
So also when we
understand disabilities,
we need to understand
what will be the Governance Models.
What will be the laws
that we need to cover.
We talked a lot about Web
Content Accessibility Guidelines
I know, so I didn't—I didn't
miss some of really great talks
between yesterday and today,
really great talks about
different normatives,
like Section 508 or WAI-ARIA,
so that is great.
So if we understand what
will be our governance model
in terms of the digital
product that we are creating,
that will be really great, because
for example talking about
United States, for example,
we need to consider International Levels,
Federal Levels or state levels
depending on the industry.
Now taking—keeping in mind
the previous information,
what will be the Best Practices in terms
of accessibility to create better sites?
to be participant in inclusive economies,
and also make this kind of
digital transformation?
And I would like to start saying
you need to define the status quo.
And why'd I say that?
A couple of days back I needed
to start working with a project.
I needed to just let some clients that
why it's important accessibility.
And that's the question that I received.
Do you know how much is the percentage
of people with disabilities
who access the site?
I feel that way.
Why?
Because some people think that
disability is just a number
and this one—
this is not good.
So we can just not disregard
people with disabilities,
because yeah it's—is that it?
No, we need to be really inclusive
when we are creating sites.
So I would like to mention
this project The Valuable 500.
This product project is
led by Caroline Casey
which is great you need to listen to—
listening her talking.
So she is great
and she led on a specific
survey with different leaders—
business leaders of great companies
and one of the topics that
she discovered was that 66—
sorry 56 percent of the global managers
that are participating
on the business plans of their companies
didn't think about disability.
And as I mentioned before,
it's not accessibility,
it's disability, the main
point on the agenda
so you can start working
better accessible products.
And I would like to invite you
to just go back one year
and try to go work—to look
for the World Economic Forum,
because that was for the first time
the entire World Economic Forum
talking about inclusive
business, inclusion, diversity,
and they talk a lot about that.
And they provide some
really great recommendations
about what will be
good in terms of business
and why accessibility is very important.
So now going back to the Accessibility
Best Practices in terms of our sites,
what we need to do first?
Well, try to Reshape the Bias.
Try to include accessibility as part of
the culture of my team starting with me.
If I did,
I am the leader, right?
because it's important to
start thinking strategically
and create best practices in our team.
Now try to look for support
for executive managers.
If they understand that
accessibility is important,
you can all start creating
really great products.
And of course you need to—
advices from experts in the area,
so you will learn more about what
will be the best strategy for you
and for your digital product.
Then we have the Scope. We can do a
lot of things with accessibility.
We can include accessibility
in everything,
but sometimes we are limited and we
have some misconceptions about that.
We can create disruptive products,
innovative products just by
including accessibility.
So accessibility will be great for that.
Try to understand what is the business
need, what would be your audience,
what type of project or service are
you providing to the clients?
And try to include accessibility
in all the process.
Okay?
Now what what would be the cost?
Well, sometimes I hear people say,
accessibility is super expensive
and yes it could be expensive,
but if you include accessibility
until testing rounds,
without including since the planning,
since their requirements validation,
or since the— not including
in the design portion,
it will be really difficult
to minimize the cost.
So it will be really expensive
at that stages in the life cycle.
But if you are including best
practices since the beginning,
it will be really good for your teams.
Now Test Test Test and Test
that's the most important.
We cannot avoid the importance that
testing is the most critical part
in terms of accessibility.
Why? Because of the one hundred
percent, seventy percent of the effort
and the notification or
the clarification for the users
that the site is accessible or not,
depends on manual testing strategies.
So it's important to create
an specific strategy
when we have trained resources that can
also provide really good recommendations
in terms of accessibility,
because it will be the specific
experience of the user,
using assistive technology
and the digital product.
So we will have a real perspective
about if our site is accessible or not.
Then we have the automated tools
which is another thing that we
will cover in the next slides,
but also we need to try to
balance these two strategies
to create a really good process.
Now I would like to give you
some tips and tricks
in order to create some user stories.
If you don't have any anything
of this created in your team,
so that's the starting point.
So it's important to
create a Diverse Persona.
When we are creating the sites we
usually design what will be our,
what type of user we will have,
what will be our audience, right?
But usually we don't think about
the different abilities of the users.
Okay we usually think in
our in our final product,
but we are usually not think
so much about the audience.
So, by having this kind of tools,
you will learn what type of screen readers
you will need in order to test
and also what type of checkpoints
in design we need to apply,
before to send everything to development.
So it will be really great for
you and this is a great example.
This is a reference, you
can check the links below
and you can check that we have
some really good practices.
if we create that,
you will have a really great vision
that what will be the specifications
that we need to also consider during
development process, design process,
testing process, and in the final product.
Okay?
Now related to WordPress,
the themes, the selection of themes,
it's really really important.
Not every theme that
is trendy is accessible.
Even though if they are super shiny,
if they're… they have a lot
of colors and combinations
and super complex functional elements,
not all of them are accessible.
So that's why it's important
to keep that in mind.
And the other thing that
I would like to mention
before to proceed to the next section is:
Be Aware the Lawsuits.
Why?
Because usually when we are
thinking about accessibility,
we think about what will be the specific
technical aspects that we need to cover
when we are creating our product.
What will be the test strategy,
what will be the requirements?
However, I would like to
mention that a QA miss
will be a lawsuit.
So most of the users that impose some
lawsuits to you, or to your company
are not just mentioned that
the site is inaccessible.
It's because they
are creating the lawsuits
because you are excluding
people with disabilities.
So that's why it's important to
keep in mind even the small details
in terms of accessibility,
because this is really important.
Now what are the recommendations
that I have for you today?
For example, if we're
talking about WordPress
you will have like a Quick Start Guide.
So you will have an
Accessibility Handbook.
You will find information
about training resources,
you will have best practices in terms
of design and content creation,
because it's important to create
accessible content as well
and the visual presentation of the pages
should be clear and easy to understand,
even though the digital
product X is complex itself.
And then you will have some
checklist testing strategies
and also you will find some, the
most common accessibility defects.
So you will be able to identify properly
what will be the strategy to follow
in terms of development or
design of quality assurance, for example.
Those two options are,
I love these two options.
I think the information that is included
in these blocks are really good
and you will find really best
practices for developers,
very technical so that is great in
terms to apply best practices
to existing components on your sites.
And also you will have some
tools to evaluate your site
and with really great references.
Also one of the things that
I like the most of those blogs
are related to some
aspects to cover public sites,
because it's different when we are working
with private sites and public sites,
the exposure will be a
little bit different.
So by having this reference
will be really great.
Then do you remember that we
talked about about Themes?
Okay we have a really great future here.
Actually when you are
going to the theme directory,
you will find a tag that
says Accessibility Ready.
So as soon as you select that,
you will find a list of different
themes that are accessible.
However, I would like to recall that
even though you are clicking this label
and you are seeing some
themes that are accessible,
you need to take care of the
opportunities for improvement
that we can also apply
after, to select this theme.
Just keep an eye on that.
Then we have some
WordPress Accessibility Tools,
for example, I would like
to mention in two ways.
The first tool—the first one is
the WordPress Accessibility Plugin.
It is really good.
You can use it and integrate
to your WordPress pages
and try to make some
audits using this plugin.
And actually it's important to have
an specific strategy for automation.
As I mentioned before, the
most important is to cover
the manual portion.
But actually when we are
also using automated tools,
we can cover a really great
aspects in terms of code.
So in this slide I'm providing you
some of the best tools that I work with
in the past years and
this is really great for you.
And it's important to mention that
it's a combination of tools
that you can have better results.
I cannot say that just by using the
WordPress Accessibility Plugin is the one.
No, probably you can use it to mix
for example, with the Axe or expert
or together with Accessibility Insights,
because this kind of tools will provide you
different reference, technical reference,
so you can have some reference from
one and some reference for others.
So you can create a really great strategy.
Then based on the screen readers,
One of the most common
questions that I have
when I work with different projects is:
"What about the screen readers?"
They usually ask if there is the—
like what is the most critical screen
reader that I need to to consider
when we are creating?
Well, I can say that it depends.
It depends of the analytics of your site.
For example, if the most
visited browser is Chrome
so you can need to try to design
your strategy based on Chrome,
but actually there is a combination
of the screen readers that work,
that works really good with Chrome
and so on.
So and now in on the
screen I'm presented to you
what is, sorry, what is the best
combination that you can keep in mind
when we are working with
the screen readers?
Actually you need to also consider if you
are working with native applications,
because it will be a little
bit different, right?
in terms of screen readers
and the combination.
It will be different in
terms of gestures, also,
because we need to use gestures
and other additional tools that we can
apply to improve the accessibility.
And I will give you a gift.
In this case, Include
People with Disabilities.
It's important just to don't take…
just for granted that all the checkpoints
that you are doing at are enough.
So this is a really great page
that I want to provide you.
The name of the page is Fable.
So you will find people with disabilities
as part of the board of this company,
so they can provide you in real time,
what are the most common
defects of your page.
We, in this page have specialized
users in screen readers,
in magnification tools and
also in code best practices,
so they can provide you the tools you need
in order to create a really great content.
Then a couple of takeaways about this
project is try to reshape your bias.
Try to think differently,
try to educate yourself
and try to unlearn things
because usually when we are
working in the technical part
we are super-structured, right?
And we usually try to follow rules,
but in this case,
we need to think differently.
We need to just think in ways
that are not common
when we are talking about accessibility.
So that's important to reshape their bias.
Also always think in your users.
There is no more important to an
honest feedback from your users,
So, try to keep in mind
the user experience.
What will be the experience
of an screen reader user.
So you can connect with different
companies depending of the state you are,
or depending of the country you are,
there are specific like
companies or services
that you can send your link
and those persons with disabilities
can help you how to validate,
what is the current experience
from them in the site,
so they can give you real
and honest feedback about your site
so please keep in mind that option.
And also, it's important to
ask for expert advice. Why?
Because sometimes when we start
creating the accessibility process,
we—the learning curve is really long,
okay, because we need to understand
what will be the success criteria
that we need to cover in terms of
the development code,
what will be… when will be enough
to have the successful criteria,
or when can do more in terms
of that success criteria.
So that's, it's really important
to ask for expert advice.
And definitely, and the last one is,
if you are an entrepreneur
you are a business lead,
you are working creating products,
you are working creating services,
please always keep
accessibility in your agenda.
Try to don't avoid this comment,
this conversation,
because it's really important.
You are creating opportunities to
make more people with disabilities
just get a really good education
and some new job opportunities
and everything related to
knowledge management, etc.
So if you are creating this kind of
projects, thinking also in inclusion,
that would be really great.
So and also I would like to keep
keep keep in touch with anybody
so I would like to provide
my point of contact.
So that's it, thank you very much.
All right that was awesome Merary,
I learned, I learned a lot.
Your slides were wonderful.
We do have plenty of time for questions,
so and we have a couple questions here,
but if anyone else does have questions
make sure you add them to the chat,
so we can, we can ask those.
So the first question is, how would you
persuade a company about the benefits
of developing and implementing an
accessibility strategy in less than
in less than five minutes.
Okay that's a really good question
and a difficult one to answer,
because one of the most important
things for companies is
how will be my benefit,
in terms of money, right?
If we are including accessibility.
And when we talk about accessibility,
accessibility,
we will not receive that money during,
after the first implementation.
It will be with a time,
so make the different business
owners or leaders understand
that vision is a little bit difficult.
But they notice with the time when
we create really good metrics,
when we can create prototypes,
when we have some empathy labs,
for example, you can create also
empathy labs in your own company.
So you can have real users,
real, sorry, I don't want to say that,
people with disabilities
just testing different sites
and also you as a owner of this product,
you can test using different tools
so you can understand what is the
current behavior for different users.
So based on that experience,
you can create a different atmosphere
so they will able to understand,
dependent of the products.
So we can earn a really great response
and then we have just kind of wait for
better responses from other leaders,
so depending on the business as well so.
Right, that was less than five minutes so.
Okay.
Perfect!
The next question is, as
an accessibility and US 508 expert,
do you think that companies that
currently use WordPress as a CMS
or a platform to create content,
can be exposed to legal lawsuits
due to their lack of accessibility?
Oooh, that's a question that
is important to answer and yes,
definitely yes.
So you need to take care about all details
when we are talking about CMS,
it's critical to also use
other type of normatives
or best practices like ATAG
which is one of the the ones that
you can integrate with the WCAG
and also with the Section 508 and try
to create a best strategy for CMS,
but yes, you can be affected about that.
Okay, all right and then
we've got one more question I see right now
and it is, have you tried
the latest version of WordPress
and did you see any major
issues with accessibility?
Well, yes I saw a couple of things,
mostly of the standards in keyboard
navigation for some functional components.
And so there is important to understand
what are the keyboard
navigation best practices
you can find that information
when you are using WAI-ARIA.
So there is an specific
chapter talking about
what will be the keyboard expectations
so you can use that as reference,
but yes that's the most common
like diff, I don't want to say difficult,
but the most common error that I noticed
which is the keyboard navigation
or the spec the keyboard navigation for
some component, functional components.
Okay fabulous. Thank you for
taking the time to answer those.
I also had a question, because
you talked about personas, and in…
I'm in marketing and so you know we've
taken the time to talk about personas,
but actually this was very enlightening
because we actually hadn't considered
accessibility within that
and I just was wondering,
how do you go about gathering data
to incorporate disabilities into personas?
and how do you prioritize, you know,
as you're saying these different levels of
accessibility and different disabilities.
I know from experience developing personas
could be a full-time job
[laughing]
in some cases, so.
Yes. Well actually,
one of the best practices that
I learned with the past years is
try to understand properly
what is the information
included in the WCAG guidelines.
So based on the different
success criteria that we have,
we also have some specific sections that
we can find a scenario they are looking to
solve, when when we have
users with these kind of abilities
or using a specific type
of assistive technology.
So based on that experience and also
providing just the site to a specific
projects that include
people with disabilities
so they also can provide
you some reference.
And one of the other things that
that I noticed as well was that
include people with
disabilities in your team,
so they have a different perspective,
so they can provide you some reference
about how they access the site.
Because sometimes when we are working
with the screen readers and everything
we have our own experience, right?
but we are not users from of
this assistive technologies,
so by having users that are
experts with assistive technology,
we also have some different visions.
But also I have some lists that
we have already created
also I can talk with you later and
share with you some information
and that can help you out with that.
Okay. Wonderful, wonderful,
thank you very much.
Again I don't see any more
questions right here,
but you did an amazing job so
much, so much good information.
So I just want to say
thank you so much again
and thank you to everyone for attending
this session with Merary and I.
You can continue the conversation
on the WordPress Accessibility Day site
on the page for this talk.
Merary provided her contact
information as well, so…
and you can continue to follow the
event conversation on Twitter @wpad2020
and #wpaccessibilityday.
So don't forget to attend the next talk
which is The Case for
Captions with Abha Thakor
which will be actually on a
different YouTube stream.
The link is posted there
in the YouTube chat and you can
also access it from the homepage of
the WordPress Accessibility Day site.
So we'll be hopping on over there
in about 20, 23ish minutes,
so yeah we will see you there after
the break. Thanks again everyone.
Thank you very much, bye.